[Music]
if you randomize overweight adolescence
into one of two groups in which they're
either advised to drink eight cups of
water a day or not what happens after 6
months uh the first question you always
have to ask with Interventional studies
is did the study participants actually
comply uh both groups started out
drinking around two cups a day and so
the study was designed mind to see if
there's a weight loss benefit of
consuming six extra cups of water
unfortunately the difference in water
intake between the groups came out to be
less than a cup and a half which wasn't
enough to show any benefit only one or
two teens in the water group reportedly
reached the target
intake to improve compliance another set
of researchers asked kids to check their
P the group of overweight 9 to 12 year
olds randomized to the water
intervention were told to increased our
water intake to the point their urine
became straw colored a pale yellow still
not every kid complied but those who did
lost significantly more weight and
inspired by these small pilot studies
and early successes with school-based
interventions in Europe researchers
launched the most ambitious study yet
involving more than a million students
in New York City Public Schools they
compared obesity rat and weight gain in
schools that implement imped cooled fast
filtered water dispensers compared to
control schools that hadn't and the
increased water access appeared to
translate into less weight gain and
lower rates of overweight kids at the
very least we should stop prohibiting
water from classrooms the accompanying
editorial in the ama's Pediatrics
Journal was entitled The Power of a
simple intervention to improve student
health Just Add
Water couldn't that result just be
explained by decreased consumption of
soft drinks the study was performed a
decade after New York City schools had
already removed soda from all the
vending
machines they still sold low-fat milk
though and that's what the researchers
suspect May account for their findings
the 12% drop in milk purchases after the
water machines were installed milk
intake like soda results in weight gain
this is true for skim milk even just
straight Dairy protein pure way or
casine beverages without the sugars
naturally occurring in milk The
increased fat Mass from drinking milk
May in part be from the increased
insulin secretion caused by milk protein
even dairy industry funded Studies have
found that drinking less than a cup of
milk with a low glycemic index meal can
exaggerate the insulin Spike as much as
if you just eaten high glycemic white
bread while milk can impair fat burning
water may have the opposite effect to
get to the bottom of the water and
weight loss question tightly controlled
metabolic experiments were performed in
which whole body protein and fat
breakdown were measured under different
degrees of hydration well hydrated
individuals experienced The Best of Both
Worlds increased fat burning and
decreased protein breakdown the way the
body responds to high water intake is
similar to how it responds to acute
fasting a switching towards fat as a
fuel source while trying to spare the
muscle these were proof of principle
experiments however with limited real
world relevance as the high fluid states
were induced not only by having
participants drink 10 cups of water over
12-hour period but also by dripping
extra free water straight into their
veins and even giving them an
anti-diuretic hormone to cause them to
retain even more water there are however
mechanisms by which our daytoday
hydration stat can affect our
metabolism when we get dehydrated our
blood volume actually shrinks this drop
is detected by our kidneys that releases
an enzyme into our bloodstream that
triggers the Cascade that results in the
formation of a hormone called
Angiotensin Angiotensin causes us to
become thirsty and constricts our blood
vessels to compensate for the diminished
blood volume that's actually how a
popular class of blood pressure lowering
medications work the Ace in ACE
inhibitors like captopril stands for
Angiotensin converting enzyme that's not
all that Angiotensin does though drip it
on human fat cells in a Petri dish and
they start piling in more fat this may
help explain why those with higher
Angiotensin levels in their bloodstream
tend to be heavier the thought is that
those who don't drink enough end up with
chronically elevated Angiotensin levels
which can lead to weight gain the most
convincing evidence comes from genetic
study showing that those born
predisposed to higher Angiotensin levels
are significantly more likely to become
obese we can keep our levels down in the
normal range though by staying
adequately
hydrated so how much water should we
drink every day unless you have a
condition like heart or kidney failure
or your physician otherwise advises you
to restrict your fluid intake here's how
much water I recommend drinking every
day for weight loss based on the
Institute of medicine's adequate intakes
assuming moderate physical activity at
moderate ambient
temperatures though many May distrust
the safety of tap water bottled water
maybe no safer cleaner or higher in
quality than water straight out of the
faucet there are risks to drinking too
much water though even healthy kidneys
may only be able to handle about three
cups of water an hour beyond that we
risk washing the electrolytes out of our
brain with potentially lethal
consequences um can you just drink a
sports drink instead no in fact there's
a high-profile case of a high school
athlete who died after drinking two
gallons of Gatorade drinking too much of
anything can be dangerous
[Music]